Finding Aid for Edward Gajec Papers 1935-1995
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Edward Gajec Papers
1935-1995
1970-1990
Gajec, Edward, 1918-
9833 Aa 2
Musician and music educator active in Detroit, Michigan area Polish and ethnic music circles, papers include correspondence, publicity material and photographs relating to ethnic music festivals and organizations.
2.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Lucile Gajec and came to the library in 1998. Donor no. 8528. Additions have been received.
The collection is open for research.
Edward Gajec was a musician, a music educator, a technician for the Detroit Board of Education, and a promoter of ethnic festivals. Gajec was born in 1918, and was educated at Detroit's Cass Technical High School and Wayne State University. In the 1950s, Gajec organized bands and orchestras which played at Polish community events, and was active in the Detroit-Hamtramck Polish community. In the 1960s, he helped organize ethnic festivals in downtown Detroit, as well as the annual Freedom Festival, which was jointly celebrated by Windsor and Detroit. In addition to his work on the festivals, Gajec was involved in Detroit's International Institute and promoted ethnic radio broadcasts. He worked as an equipment technician for the Detroit Board of Education from 1967 to 1997, when he retired. Gajec remained active in local musical and ethnic activities until his death in 1998.
The Gajec papers consist of correspondence, brochures, programs, newspaper clippings, and photographs. The material in the collection documents Detroit's ethnic communities in the 1950-1990 period, focusing on established ethnic organizations and festivals. The collection also contains material relating to amateur musical activities and a small amount of material relating to civic organizations. The papers are organized in three series: Biographical, Ethnic Activities and Organizations, and Other Activities and Organizations.
Subjects:
Gajec, Edward, 1918-; Detroit (Mich.)--Population.; Ethnic festivals--Michigan--Detroit.; Ethnography--Michigan--Detroit.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Festivals--Michigan--Detroit.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical
  The Biographical series consists of one folder of biographical/memorial material and one folder of photographs from 1944.
  - Clippings and correspondence, 1956-1998 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 1944 (Box 1)
- Ethnic Activities and Organizations
  The Ethnic Activities and Organizations series consists of material relating to ethnic activities and organizations in Detroit. The series includes files relating to specific ethnic groups and festivals, to large, multi-ethnic festivals, such as the annual Detroit-Windsor Freedom Festival, and to multi-ethnic organizations and activities intended to promote ethnic awareness.
  - African American material, 1970-1987; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - American Festival; U.S. veterans, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Arab material, 1972-1992 (Box 1)
  - Armenian Festival, 1971-1990 (Box 1)
  - Captive Nations Festival, 1971-1983 (Box 1)
  - Estonian material, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Ethnic Bicentennial, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Ethnic Festival; Detroit, 1972-1984 (Box 1)
  - Far Eastern Festival, 1971-1973 (Box 1)
  - Filipino material, 1970-1985 (Box 1)
  - Freedom Festival; Detroit-Windsor
    - 1959-1985 (Box 1)
    - Publicity photographs, 1965 (Box 1)
  - German Festival, 1970-1990 (Box 1)
  - Greek Festival, 1970-1977 (Box 1)
  - Indian material, 1970-1984; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - International Festival; Hamtramck, 1957-1964 (Box 1)
  - International Flag Festival, 1959 (Box 1)
  - International Institute, 1969-1984 (Box 1)
  - Irish Festival, 1970-1990 (Box 1)
  - Italian material, 1970-1995 (Box 1)
  - Latin American material, 1971-1991 (Box 1)
  - Lithuanian material, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - Mexican material, 1962-1986 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous festival material, 1974-1992 (Box 1)
  - Polish material
    - Community material, 1937-1995; 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Festivals, 1970-1993; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Hamtramck materials, 1962-1986 (Box 2)
    - Hamtramcki Yacht Klub, 1975-1982 (Box 2)
    - Jean J. Jalmuzynski, 1941-1952 (Box 2)
    - Mlody Teatr; Detroit, 1948-1969 (Box 2)
    - Newspapers
      - Hamtramck Weekly Observer, 1984 (Box 2)
      - Polish Daily News records, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
    - Pamphlets, 1957-1987; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Puerto Rican material, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - Russian material, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Scandinavian material, 1933-1980; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Slovak material, 1970-1980 (Box 2)
  - State Fair Festival of Nations, 1939-1941 (Box 2)
  - Ukrainian material, 1963-1986 (Box 2)
  - Wayne State University; ethnic activities, 1972-1974 (Box 2)
  - Yugoslav Festival, 1979 (Box 2)
- Other Activities and Organizations
  The Other Activities and Organizations series is divided into four subseries, Civic Interests, Musical Material, Radio Material, and Photographs. The Civic Interests subseries consists of material related to Detroit city and neighborhood organizations and issues. The Musical subseries contains material documenting Gajec's involvement in musical organizations, education, and businesses. It includes concert programs, papers from the bands Gajec led or performed with, professional correspondence, and musical education material. The Radio subseries contains publicity material and memoranda from Detroit radio stations. The Photographs subseries contains undated unidentified photographs of musical and theatrical subjects.
  - Civic Interests
    - Detroit Public Schools, Region Two Office, Special Task Force Committee; Western YMCA Pre-Parole Program, 1982-1984 (Box 2)
    - Central Business District Association; Detroit, 1971-1990 (Box 2)
    - Creative Arts Alliance, 1980-1982 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous civic projects; Detroit, 1960-1980 (Box 2)
  - Musical Material
    - Concert Programs, 1935-1963 (Box 2)
    - Bands and Orchestras
      - Co-eds All Girl Orchestra, 1941-1955 (Box 3)
      - Hamtramck Philharmonic Orchestra, 1940-1967 (Box 3)
      - Hamtramck Symphony/ Concert, 1984-1988 (Box 3)
      - Heritage Concert, 1992-1996 (Box 3)
      - Redford Symphony, 1960-1994; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Professional materials; musical
      - Business and education; correspondence and records, 1938-1960 (Box 3)
      - Josef Cherniavsky, 1948-1956 (Box 3)
  - Radio Material
    - WJLB Radio, 1965-1975 (Box 3)
    - WMZK Radio; ethnic broadcasts, 1969-1983 (Box 3)
    - WDET, WHFR; ethnic broadcasts, 1990-1991 (Box 3)
  - Photographs
    - Photographs of musical and theatrical performers (largely unidentified) (Box 3)